kodomo no goro no yume wa
The dream I had when I was a child,
子供の頃の夢は　色褪せない落書きで
iroase nai rakugaki de
were drawn to my heart's desire
omou mama kaki suberasete
with scribbles that wouldn't fade away
思うまま書き滑らせて
描く未来へとつながる
egaku mirai he to tsunagaru
and are connected to the future i draw.
Utawarerumono
sumiwataru sora
The clear skies
澄み渡る空　果てしないほど青く
hateshinai hodo aoku
were endlessly blue.
mujaki na kokoro ni
And my innocent heart,
無邪気な心に　充たされ魅かれてく
mitasare hikareteku
being satisfied, was attracted to them.
yagate jiyuu ni tobimawareru
I finally obtained wings
やがて自由に飛びまわれる
翼(はね)を手に入れて
hane wo teni irete
with which I could fly freely.
muku na hitomi wa motometeku
I want to go to the end of the skies
無垢な瞳は求めてく
空の向こうへ　行きたいな
sora no mukou he ikitai na
which my pure eyes desire.
kore tonai negai kara
If one wish could be granted
止め処ない願いから　一つだけ叶うのなら
hitotsu dake kanau no nara
out of countless others...
dare ni mo yuzuri taku wa nai
I feel that it should be to grab onto a dream
誰にも譲りたくはない
夢を掴みたいと思うよ
yume wo tsukamitai to omou yo
and never be tempted to let go.
kodomo no goro no yume wa
The dreams I had when I was a child,
子供の頃の夢は　色褪せない落書きで
iroase nai rakugaki de
were drawn eternally,
itsuwademo kaki tsuzukerareta
with scribbles that wouldn't fade away
いつまでも描き続けられた
願う未来へとつながる
negau mirai he to tsunagaru
and are connected to the future I wish for.
At the End of the Battle
It's been less than a month since
the war with Shikeripechim.
シケリペチムとの戦から
一月足らずですが
Recovery efforts have progressed swiftly.
復興は急速に進んでおります
So it appears.
そのようだな
Isn't it incredible how much that razed field
has changed right before our very eyes.
すごいですね
焼け野原だった所が 見る見る内に
One cannot underestimate
people's will to live.
人が生きる力というものを
侮ってはなりませぬ
That is true.
そうだな
-えっへーい
-アハハハ アハ ハハハハハハ
It's the Emperor!
オウルォ様
Ah! The Emperor!
-あ オウルォ様
-フフ
僕らも 早く強くなって
一緒に戦えるようになります
We're going to grow up strong so that
we can fight together for you!
We're going to fight for you!
なります
My, how promising.
-なんと頼もしい
-いくぞお　いや 来い
へへい　やあ
えい
By the time you're all grown up,
there won't be any more wars.
皆が大きくなる頃には
もう戦は無くなってるわ
So, there won't be any need to fight.
だから戦う必要なんて無いの
Okay?
She is right.
そのとおりだ
You all help your fathers and mothers, and do
your best to bring your lives back to normal.
皆はお父さんお母さんを助け
暮らしが元通りになるように 頑張るんだ
Yes, sir!
はあい
えへっ はははっ
ウフッ
For Kuccha Keccha, we would like to
send one of our agents
クッチャ・ケッチャには
私たちの方から人を遣わし
to facilitate the reestablishment
of your government.
執政を務めさせたいと思います
Will that be acceptable?
よろしいですか？
Yes, on behalf of the citizens of Kuccha Keccha,
we thank you for your kindness.
はい
皆様の恩情
クッチャ・ケッチャの民になり代わり
御礼申し上げます
This should do for Kuccha Keccha.
クッチャ・ケッチャに関しては
これでよろしいかと
However, it will not be so easy
for Shikeripechim.
ですが
シケリペチムは そうはいかないでしょう
Their imperial capital was
burned to the ground,
王都は焼け落ち
多くの男手を戦で失っています
and they have lost many of
their men to the war.
むう
Only about ten percent of the population of
Shikeripechim's capital city have survived.
シケリペチムの都で生き残ったのは
一割程度です
It will be difficult for them to rebuild
solely on their own.
彼らだけで立て直すのは 難しいでしょう
However...
しかし
We cannot leave it as a wasteland either.
荒れるに任せよとも言えません
The territory must eventually be
taken into our dominion,
領土の併合は避けられないでしょう
and the reconstruction of the
Imperial City will...
その場合 王都の復興は
We will abandon it.
放棄しよう
It would be difficult to rebuild
in that razed location.
あの焼き尽くされた地を
復興するのは難しい
The survivors can live in a new land.
生き残った者たちは
新たな土地で暮らせばいいのだ
Away from Niwe's...
ニウェの ん
It is a good opportunity to escape
from a detestable past.
忌まわしい過去から逃れる いい機会だ
We will abandon the Imperial City.
王都は 放棄する
Are you tired?
お疲れになりましたか？
Yeah...
What's the matter?
どうした
あっ いえ 何でも
Oh, it's nothing.
Oh, I know, let me massage your shoulders.
そうだ 肩でもお揉みしましょうか
I'm sorry.
すまないな
It's nothing.
いいえ
You're working too hard, Hakuoro-san.
You need to take a break.
ハクオロさんは働きすぎなんですよ
少しは休んだ方がいいと思います
I think so too, but...
そうは思うんだが
It's not enough to just think about it!
思うだけじゃ駄目です！
ウッフフ
You are a beast that brings about disaster!
汝は 災いを運ぶ獣よ
-はっ　はっ はあ
-お前がいる限り この世から戦は無くならぬ
As long as you exist, wars will
not cease in this world!
-クーッカッカッカッカッカッ　ほおれ
-くうっ
See there? Look...
このように
クーッカッカッカッカッ
Your hands are covered in blood!
-うわっ　うっ
-汝の手は血まみれよ
-クーッカッカッカッカッカッカッカッ
-うっ ううっ
-うわあああああ
-クーッカッカッカッカッカッカッカッカッ
Your Highness?
聖上
It looks like your room is made.
部屋が出来たようだな
Yes, I have not words to express
my gratitude to you
某のような者に過分のお心遣い
for giving such generous
consideration to one lowly as I.
感謝の言葉もございません
Do not be so formal about it.
そう堅苦しく考えるな
Think of this place as your home,
you are free to do as you wish.
自分の家だと思って
自由にしてくれればいい
I do not need you to guard me.
護衛など不要だぞ
I cannot permit otherwise!
そうは参りませぬ
Being conscientious is good, but...
フッ 生真面目なのはいいが
Your Highness!
聖上
Oh, goodness.
ええっと
This is ready to eat.
Now for some drinking snacks...
-これ食べ頃
-あとは魚魚っと
If you take too much...
-あまり持ち出すと
-うっ
Eruruu is sure to find out.
エルルゥにばれるぞ
見つかるなんて不覚ですわ
I can't believe we got caught!
Wha...
Do not worry too much about them.
ま いちいち気にしないことだ
S.. Sire...
お いやあ総大将
Hey, Commander!
What is going on?
何をしている？
Well, the young general said that
he wanted a sparing match.
何 ねえ
若大将が
本組手するって言い出しやしてねえ
With Benawi?
ベナウィと？
ぷふううう
ねえっ
My lord...
若様
ぬう ぬうう
ぬうう
He's pretty good.
やるじゃねえか
En guarde.
行きます
There!
ここだあっ
ぬう
I got you!
もらったあ
ぬわああああ
That was splendid, however...
見事です
が 戦いは常に２手３手先を読むもの
In battle, you must always plan
two to three moves ahead.
Thinking that your opponent is powerless
can cost you your life.
相手が無力になったという思い込みは
命取りですよ
With that said, you have improved
considerably compared to before.
とはいえ
あの頃から比べれば 格段の進歩
腕を上げましたね
ふん
Doesn't mean a thing if I can't win!
勝てなければ 意味は無い
All right! Let's have a toast to the two of you!
よっしゃあ
２人の健闘を讃えて酒盛りだ
Okay, you lugs, let's party!
野郎ども
飲むぞお
Yeah!
Goodness, drinking from midday!
もう
昼間っからなんて
I do not mind.
構わないさ
After all, everyone's laughter
has returned, right?
こうして 皆の笑い声が
戻ったのだからな
Camus, you're drinking too much.
カミュ
飲み過ぎだぞ
Mister...
おじさま
No matter how much I drink,
I'm still thirsty.
飲んでも飲んでも 乾きが止まらないの
Stop it already.
もう止すんだ
I wonder what's wrong with me?
私
どうしちゃったのかな
Maybe I've got some weird disease.
もしかして
変な病気になっちゃったのかな
Camus?
カミュ？
うくっ
Oww...
-痛ったったった
-言わんこっちゃ無い
See, I told you.
Are you all right?
大丈夫か？
Camus!
カミュ？
Urutori, Camus is...
ウルト
カミュが
Are you okay?
大丈夫？
When you said you were thirsty,
I thought it couldn't be...
喉が乾くと言っていたから
まさかとは思っていたんだけれど
Shall I call Eruruu?
エルルゥを呼ぶか？
Ah... No, please don't worry.
ああ いえ
心配は要りません
Here, let's go back to your room.
ほら
-一緒に部屋へ戻りましょう
-くっ うっ
くう
Is she really okay?
本当に 平気なのか？
Yes, I'm sorry to have bothered you.
はい
すみませんでした
What the heck am I?
私は一体
何者なのだ
You are the beast that brings about disaster.
汝は 災いを運ぶ獣よ
To me, you are who you are, Hakuoro-san.
私にとってハクオロさんは
ハクオロさんなんです
Eruruu...
エルルゥ
The citizens of Shikeripechim wish to
return to their imperial city.
シケリペチムの民が
王都へと帰りたがっています
To those ruins?
あの 廃墟にですか？
They wish to rebuild it with their own hands.
自分たちの手で 復興させたいのでしょう
That's crazy.
無茶だ
With the number of those left, it will take
them over ten years to rebuild.
あの残された人数では
10年かかっても終わるまい
Did you not tell them to relocate
to this country?
この国で暮らせとは伝えなかったのか
I did, however...
伝えました
ですが
Even if it is in ruins now, it is still their homeland
where they were born and raised.
たとえ今は廃墟でも
彼らが生まれ育った故郷ですから
Homeland, huh?
故郷か
Perhaps you have reservations about
them returning to that place?
やはり
あそこに戻すには 懸念がありますか
That they will be still be tied to
their past with Niwe?
ニウェという過去に
縛られるのではないかと
What would you have us do, Your Highness?
いかがいたしますか
聖上
Let me think about this for a bit.
少し 考えさせてくれ
In a certain village, there was a man
and a woman who were in love.
とある集落に
とても仲睦まじい男と女がいました
However, the man had to go
to war as a soldier.
しかし男は 兵として
戦場へ行かねばなりませんでした
So, they made a vow to each other.
そこで２人は 約束を交わしたのです
When the man returned from the war,
the two would be wed.
男が戻ってきたら一緒になろうと
But the man got wounded in the war,
and as he thought he was dying...
男は戦場で傷付き
倒れました
もはやこれまでかと思った時
Hakuoro-sama?
ハクオロ様
Remain as you are.
そのまま
Please continue your story.
話を続けてあげてくれ
Yes!
あ はい
As he thought he was dying,
he noticed a brightly shining star.
思った時
星の明かりがいつにも増して
明るいことに気が付きました
This star lit his way home in the night.
星の輝きは夜道を照らし
Lifting his spirits, it led him
safely back to his village.
男を励まし
無事に故郷へと導いたのです
However, the woman was nowhere to be found.
しかしそこに 女の姿はありませんでした
It was then that the man realized
そして男は知ったのです
that the star that guided him home
was his beloved woman.
自分を導いてくれたあの星こそ
愛する女であったことを
The woman had died of the plague before
the man could return to her.
女は男が帰るのを待たずに
流行り病で亡くなっていたのでした
She became a star goddess,
and it was her love,
星神となり
愛する男を故郷へと帰した女の想い
which returned her beloved
safely back to his village.
The Great God was so touched by her
devotion that when the man died,
その想いに打たれた大神が
男が死んだ時
he put the man's soul up in the heavens.
その魂を天に導きました
Finally united as husband and wife,
夫婦となった２人の星は
the two stars continue to shine
brightly in the night sky.
今も夜空に輝いているのです
Could I also...
ユズハも
Could I also become a star?
ユズハもお星様になれますか？
Then I could shine brightly for everyone.
そしたら 今度はユズハが
皆を照らしてあげられるのに
Yuzuha...
ユズハ
I want to become a star.
ユズハは
お星様になりたいです
You will.
なれますよ
You'll fall in love, nurture that love
and bear and raise a child.
ユズハちゃんが恋をして
愛を育んで
子を産み 育て
If you live today and tomorrow to the fullest,
I'm sure you'll become a star!
今日を そして明日を一生懸命生きれば
きっとお星様になれます
ウフッ それはまだ先のこと
But that is still far in the future.
But I'm...
でも ユズハは
You must believe that tomorrow will
be more wonderful than today,
明日は昨日より素敵な日だと信じるの
and live life to its fullest.
そして精いっぱい生きる
You see, "tomorrow" is something
that we all need.
私たちに必要なのは
明日なんだから
Okay!
はい
Wow...
わあ
I didn't realize it was this bad.
ここまでひどいとは
It would be a tremendous undertaking
to rebuild this area.
復興させるとすれば
大変な作業になるでしょう
Perhaps the only option after all
is to abandon this place.
やはり 放棄するしかないのでしょうか
Sire?
聖上？
I want to think this over. Give me some time.
少し考えたい
時間をくれ
What are you looking at?
-何を見ているんです？
-ん？
There is not even a single blade of grass left.
草
一つ生えない
This is what I leave in my wake.
これが
私の通り過ぎた後だ
私は
What a horrid creature I am.
何ともおぞましい存在ではないか
That's not true!
そんなことはありません
Even in this scorched place...
こんな焼け跡に
The last time we were here,
I spread some seeds.
前に来た時に 種を蒔いておいたんです
Why?
どうして？
If you sow the seeds,
the greenery will come back.
種を蒔けば 緑は戻ります
If you don't sow, nothing will grow.
蒔かなければ何も生えない
What's important is the will to
grow something anew.
大切なのは
新しい何かを育ててゆく気持ちです
So we need tomorrow more
than yesterday, huh?
私たちに必要なのは
昨日より明日か
Will I ever find the answers that I seek too?
いずれは私の探している答えも
見つかるだろうか
Yes! I'm sure you will.
はい
きっと
Then we need to start by rebuilding this city.
ならば
まずこの都を立て直すことからだな
Camus?
カミュ？
Ah! You came for me...
来てくれたんだ
Come, let's play together!
おいで 一緒に遊ぼう
ウフフ
It all seems like nothing of this world.
これは
まるでこの世の光景ではないみたいだ
Not of this world... I see.
この世の
そうか
Then the priestess of the Onkamiyamukai...
ではあれは
オンカミヤムカイのカムナギ
A girl adored by something not of this world...
この世のならざるものに
愛される少女
I am a warrior who goes by the name Genjimaru.
某 ゲンジマルと申す武士にござりまする
My master wishes to meet
with you, Lord Hakuoro,
某のあるじが
ハクオロ王に御目通り願いたく
and I have come to escort you.
お迎えに参上した次第
You have been spying on me for some time.
しばらく前から
私をうかがっていた者だな
What do you want at this hour?
こんな夜更けに何用だ
It is nothing to be anxious about.
ご懸念には及びませぬ
決して 害意あってのことではござらぬ故
I will bring you no harm.
Very well then.
いいだろう
I have brought Emperor Hakuoro.
ハクオロ王を お連れしました
I am Kuuya Amrulineulka, ruler of Kunekamun.
余がクンネカムン王
アムルリネウルカ・クーヤだ
炎さえも凍てついた
honou sae mo itetsuita
I seek the solitude
kokuno naka moto mu
that freezes even flames.
孤独の中求む
tamashi kara musubitsuki
Connecting with your soul,
魂から結びつき　私を恋い温めて
watashi wo koi atatamete
warm me with your love.
a inori no kotoba ga furue
Ah...the words of prayer tremble...
嗚呼　祈りの言葉がふるえ
a yowaki no chika kiete mo
Ah even if the faint-hearted
were to disappear...
嗚呼　弱きいのちが消えても
kurikaesu innen no nagare tadori
Following the recurring paths of fate.
くりかえす　輪廻の流れ辿り
owaranai sekai no shukumei wo mitsumeteru
I gaze upon the never-ending world's destiny.
終わらない世界の宿命を見つめてる
kurikaeshi utawareru mono tachi yo
Oh the ones being sung continuously
くりかえし　詠われる者達よ
守られてまどろむ宵
mamorarete madoromu you ni
be protected and sleep.
The Young Sovereign